<page zone="IntAct" title="User Manual" format="column">

    <section title="Contents" name="cont">

        <auto-index index="main"/>

    </section>

    <division name="main" style="numbered">



        <section title="Introduction" name="intro">

            <blockquote>
                IntAct is a protein interaction database and analysis system. It
                provides a query interface and modules to analyse interaction
                data. This manual describes the IntAct data structure and the
                components of the IntAct system.
            </blockquote>

        </section>



        <section title="IntAct data representation" name="core">

            <section title="Main objects" name="mainObject">

                <blockquote>
                    IntAct has the following main objects:
                    <ul>
                        <li><a href="#Experiment">Experiment</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#Interaction">Interaction</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#Interactor">Interactor</a></li>
                    </ul>

                    <br/>

                    <a name="mainObjectsExample"></a>
                    Example (simplified): Representation of the Interleukin 2 receptor binding:
                    One interaction object represents the complex of the alpha, beta, and gamma
                    chains which form the receptor. This interaction object is the used in the
                    second interaction object, in which the binding of Interleukin 2 to the
                    receptor is represented. Both Interaction objects are linked to an experiment,
                    in which the Interaction has been determined.
                    <img align="left"  src="./images/core/intactMainObjects2.jpg"/>
                    <img align="right" src="./images/core/intactMainObjects.jpg"/>
                    <br clear="all" />
                    The following section describes the main objects in detail.
                </blockquote>

                <section title="Experiment" name="Experiment">

                    <blockquote>
                        An Experiment object describes an experiment which has been performed
                        to generate one or more interactions. It indicates the conditions
                        in which the experiment has been performed. The description
                        broadly classifies the experiment, it does not aim at
                        providing all the necessary data to repeat the experiment. The
                        attributes of the Experiment are the
                        <dl>
                            <dt/><a href="#BioSource">BioSource</a>
                            <dd/>The biological system in which the interaction took place in the experiment.
                            <dt/>identificationMethod
                            <dd/>The experimental method by which the molecules participating in the
                            interaction have been detected.
                            <br/>Example: Mass spectrometry.
                            <dt/>interactionMethod
                            <dd/>The experimental method by which the interaction has been detected. <br/>
                            Example: yeast two hybrid.
                        </dl>
                        Each Experiment provides a list of one or more <a href="#Interaction">Interactions</a>
                        which have been determined by this Experiment. One Experiment might contain a single
                        Interaction, or many hundreds for large scale experiments.
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Experiment -->


                <section title="Interaction" name="Interaction">

                    <blockquote>
                        The Interaction object describes the interaction of two or more
                        <a href="#Interactor">Interactors</a> (proteins). As the number of Interactors in an
                        Interaction is not limited, an Interaction can describe both binary interactions,
                        which are the result of for example yeast two hybrid experiments, and interactions
                        with more than two Interactors, for example determined by "TAP" experiments.
                        The attributes of an Interaction are
                        <dl>
                            <dt/>CvInteractionType
                            <dd/>A description of the type of interaction. <br/>
                            Example: association.
                            <dt/>kD
                            <dd/>The dissociation constant.
                        </dl>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Interaction -->


                <section title="Interactor" name="Interactor">

                    <blockquote>
                        A molecule or complex participating in an Interaction. The
                        only direct attribute of an Interactor is
                        <dl>
                            <dt/><a href="#BioSource">BioSource</a>
                            <dd/>The biological system in which the interactor normally is
                            found. For a human protein, the BioSource would be "Human",
                            even if it has been expressed in E.coli in a particular
                            experiment.
                        </dl>
                        If the Interactor is a Protein, it additionally has the attributes
                        <dl>
                            <dt/>sequence
                            <dd/>The amino acid sequence of the protein.
                            <dt/>crc64
                            <dd/>The CRC64 checksum for the amino acid sequence. This
                            checksum is used to quickly detect if the amino acid sequence
                            has changed, for example during an update process. It is also
                            used to check if the amino acid sequence has potentially been
                            corrupted. <br/>
                            The
                            algorithm to compute the CRC64 is described in the ISO 3309
                            standard. The generator polynomial is x64 + x4 + x3 + x + 1.<br/>
                            Reference: Press W.H., Flannery B.P., Teukolsky S.A. and Vetterling
                            W.T. "Numerical recipes in C", 2nd ed., pp896-902, Cambridge
                            University Press (1993). (See
                            http://www.ulib.org/webRoot/Books/Numerical_Recipes/bookcpdf/c20-3.pdf)
                            It should be noted that while, in theory, two different
                            sequences could have the same CRC64 value, the likelihood that
                            this would happen is extremely low.
                        </dl>
                        An Interactor describes an "abstract" form of e.g. a protein,
                        similar to a description in a protein sequence database. One
                        protein can participate in many interactions. To describe the
                        specific conditions in which an Interactor participates in an
                        Interaction, the following additional attributes are used:
                        <dl>
                            <dt/>stoichiometry
                            <dd/>The number of units of this interactor which participate in
                            the interaction. The default is one.
                            <dt/>expressedIn
                            <dd/>A <a href="#BioSource">BioSource</a> object which describes
                            the biological system in which the protein has been
                            expressed. <br/>
                            Example: If a human protein has been expresed in E.coli,
                            expressedIn would refer to E.coli.
                            <dt/>Role
                            <dd/>The role of the Interactor in the Interaction. In a yeast
                            two hybrid experiment, each Interaction would usually have an
                            Interactor which has the role "bait" and another one which has
                            the role "prey".
                        </dl>

                        An Interactor is normally a protein. However, to model
                        hierarchical assemblies of complexes from subcomplexes, an
                        Interactor can also be an Interaction.<br/>
                        Example: To model a receptor-ligand interaction, the receptor
                        could be modeled by an interaction which describes the composition
                        of the receptor from its component proteins. Then, in another
                        Interaction, the association of receptor and ligand would be
                        described. See the <a href="#mainObjectsExample">IL-2 example</a>.<br/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Interactor -->

            </section> <!-- Main objects -->


            <section title="Auxiliary objects" name="AuxiliaryObjects">

                <blockquote>
                    The following objects are auxiliary objects, often used in several different main classes.
                </blockquote>


                <section title="BioSource" name="BioSource">

                    <blockquote>
                        <dd/>The BioSource object describes a biological system, usually a species. The attributes of a BioSource are
                        <dl>
                            <dt/>taxId
                            <dd/>The NCBI tax id, see the <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/">NCBI taxonomy server</a> or the <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/newt/index.html">NEWT taxonomy server</a>.
                            <dt/>shortLabel
                            <dd/>The shortLabel is the Swiss-Prot OS code, where available.
                            <dt/>fullName
                            <dd/>The full name is the scientific name of the species.
                        </dl>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- BioSource -->


                <section title="CvObject" name="CvObject">

                    <blockquote>
                        <dd/>IntAct makes intensive use of controlled vocabularies. Where
                        possible, data attributes are controlled vocabularies, the
                        terms are selected from a defined list instead of being free
                        text. For each attribute which is selected from a controlled
                        vocabulary, a specific CvXXXXX class exists, for example
                        CvInteractionType. Each term in a controlled vocabulary has a
                        definition, usually has crossreferences, and may have
                        additional comments.
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- CvObject -->

            </section> <!-- Auxiliary objects -->


            <section title="Common elements" name="CommonElements">

                <blockquote>
                    All main IntAct objects have
                </blockquote>

                <section title="ac" name="BasicObject.ac">

                    <blockquote>
                        The accession number. This is a unique, stable identifier
                        for an object. The same accession number will always be
                        assiciated with the same object. To reference IntAct objects
                        from outside, accession numbers should be used. The format of
                        the accession number is one or more uppercase letters, followed by a
                        dash, followed by a number. <br/>
                        In regular expression syntax:	[A-Z]\-[0-9]+.<br/>
                        Example: EBI-15
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="shortLabel" name="AnnotatedObject.shortLabel">

                    <blockquote>
                        The short label is a short, concise name to identify an
                        object. Short labels for proteins are
                        usually gene names, short labels for experiments are usually
                        the names of the first author of the publication. Short labels
                        will normally be stable, but they may change, e.g. when the
                        gene name of a protein is changed by the relevant nomenclature
                        body, e.g. HUGO. Short labels are not guaranteed to be unique,
                        e.g. if two proteins have the same primary gene name. They are
                        guaranteed to be unique for controlled vocabulary terms within each controlled vocabulary.
                        <br/>
                        Example: GOT2.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="fullName" name="AnnotatedObject.fullName">

                    <blockquote>
                        The full name of the object.<br/>
                        Example: Aspartate aminotransferase.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="Xref" name="AnnotatedObject.Xref">

                    <blockquote>
                        Crossreferences to other databases.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="Annotation" name="AnnotatedObject.Annotation">

                    <blockquote>
                        Each object may have one or more annotations associated with
                        it. Each annotation has a topic, which broadly classifies the
                        annotation, and the annotation text.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="created" name="BasicObject.created">

                    <blockquote>
                        The date the object has been created.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="updated" name="BasicObject.updated">

                    <blockquote>
                        The date the object has been updated last.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

            </section> <!-- Common elements -->

        </section>  <!-- IntAct data representation -->












        <section title="IntAct applications" name="IntAct-applications">

            Here comes the IntAct application documentation.


            <section title="Search" name="search">


                <section title="Availability" name="search.availability">

                    <blockquote>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>


                <section title="Basic Overview" name="search.Overview">

                    <blockquote>
                        The search application currently allows a text-based search by entering
                        a text string into the search text box. It is possible to obtain information
                        on experiments, protein interactions and the proteins themselves, with
                        various views used to display the data. Intact uses the concept of short
                        label which is intended to provide a way of 'more memorable identification'
                        compared to a standard Accession Number (AC), although searches by AC are
                        obviously allowed. For example a particular Experiment may have an AC of
                        EBI-14, but its short label is 'gavin' indicating a more meaningful reference
                        to the physical experiment which the entry represents. Basic points on
                        usage:

                        <ul>
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    Wildcard searching is supported - for example matches will be retrieved
                                    for strings such as EBI*, *BI-14, E*4, etc etc.</li>

                                <li>
                                    upper or lower case strings are acceptable and will be matched if they
                                    exist</li>

                                <li>
                                    currently searches progress in a certain order: proteins, then interactions,
                                    then experiments. At a lower level, specific attributes are searched by
                                    AC, short label, Xref primary ID and finally full name. This algorithm
                                    may change as the intact project matures.</li>

                                <li>
                                    Note that whilst CvObject details can be displayed via the click of a link,
                                    currently it is not possible to search for CvObjects via the text box search
                                    entry point.</li>
                            </ul>
                        </ul>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!--  -->

                <section title="Structure of Search Results" name="search.TableLayout">

                    <blockquote>
                        The basic layout of the main results page follows the structure below:

                        <br/>

                        <table BORDER="1" COLS="4" WIDTH="94%" >
                            <tr>
                                <td><b>Experiment</b></td>

                                <td><u>AC</u></td>

                                <td><u>ShortLabel</u></td>

                                <td>full name</td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td><u>CvInteraction</u></td>

                                <td><u>CvIdentification</u></td>

                                <td>BioSource</td>

                                <td></td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td>Comment topic</td>

                                <td>Comment description</td>

                                <td></td>

                                <td></td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td><u>xref database</u></td>

                                <td>primaryId</td>

                                <td>secondaryId</td>

                                <td></td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td><b>Interaction</b></td>

                                <td><u>AC</u></td>

                                <td><u>ShortLabel</u></td>

                                <td>full name</td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td><u>shortLabel1</u> [<u>b</u>], <u>shortLabel2</u> [<u>p</u>],</td>

                                <td><u>shortLabel3</u> [<u>p</u>], <u>shortLabel4</u> [p], </td>

                                <td>......................................</td>

                                <td></td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td><b>Interaction</b></td>

                                <td><u>AC</u></td>

                                <td><u>ShortLabel</u></td>

                                <td>full name</td>
                            </tr>

                            <tr>
                                <td><u>shortLabel5</u> [<u>b</u>], <u>shortLabel6</u> [<u>p</u>],</td>

                                <td><u>shortLabel7</u> [<u>p</u>], <u>shortLabel8</u> [<u>p</u>], </td>

                                <td>...........................</td>

                                <td></td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>

                        <p><a NAME="ResultsExample"></a>Searching for interactions, proteins or
                            experiments typically results in the same view - a table detailing all
                            the interactions for a particular experiment, with the short labels listed
                            of the proteins involved in the interactions. An example result screen
                            is shown below:</p>
                        <p><img SRC="./images/search/imageV3F.JPG" height="768" width="1024"/></p>
                        <p><a NAME="ExampleProteinView"></a>An example result view from clicking
                            on a Protein link is shown below:</p>
                        <p><img SRC="./images/search/image23F.JPG" height="768" width="1024"/></p>
                        <br/>
                        <p><a NAME="ExampleCvView"></a>If for example in the above screen you click
                            on 'SPTR', this will display the controlled vocabulary information for
                            the database identified with a short label of 'SPTR'. The screen looks
                            like this:</p>
                        <p><img SRC="./images/search/imageE0A.JPG" height="768" width="1024"/></p>
                        <br/>
                        <p><a NAME="ShortLabelHelp"></a>Protein short labels are links you can
                            click to get a view of the protein details. Also each protein short label
                            has a term in brackets (eg '[p]') which denotes the role that the protein
                            plays in the interaction. These terms have tooltips associated with them
                            to display the role name, and also the term is a clickable link from which
                            you can view the full details of the controlled vocabulary term which presents
                            the controlled vocabulary information for that term (eg the details held
                            to define the meaning of the term 'bait').</p>
                        <p>Since the items displayed for a search result include many items not
                            actually queried for, the items that matched the oringinal search string
                            are highlighted in <b><i>bold italic</i></b> - there is even a helpful
                            little message at the top of the results page to remind you of this. Specifically
                            the *short labels* of the matching items are highlighted, since these are
                            always displayed in every view.</p>
                        <p>Where a protein (for example) might actually occur more than once in
                            an experiment, the display is rationalised to avoid multiple presentations
                            of the same experiment - therefore all occurrences within an experiment
                            are gathered together into one experiment view.</p>
                        <p><a NAME="ButtonDefinition"></a>At the bottom of the page are a number
                            of buttons:</p>
                        <ul>
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    a button to view the full details of what is on the results page (this
                                    expands all the information currently on the page, apart from the controlled
                                    vocabulary details);</li>

                                <li>a reset button to uncheck any textboxes;</li>

                                <li>
                                    a graph button to display a graph of any selected proteins, which can be
                                    chosen by clicking the appropriate checkboxes.</li>
                            </ul>
                        </ul>
                        <a NAME="ExamplDetailView"></a>Clicking on the 'Detail View' button expands
                        all protein details - a partial view of an example resulting page is shown
                        below:
                        <p><img SRC="./images/search/imageGKH.JPG" height="768" width="1024"/></p>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Basic Overview -->

            </section> <!-- Search -->












            <section title="Editor" name="editor">


                <section title="Availability" name="editor.availability">

                    <blockquote>
                        The application to edit IntAct database is only available for
                        users with the write access to it. Hence, Editor application
                        is not available to public access.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>


                <section title="Overview" name="editor.overview">

                    <blockquote>
                        The editor is a web based tool to edit IntAct database.
                        Presently, it supports following IntAct objects: CvTopic, CvCellCycle,
                        CvDatabase, CvTissue, CvModificationType, CvCellType, Protein,
                        CvComponentRole, CvFeatureType, CvCompartment, CvProductRole,
                        CvFeatureIdentification, CvInteraction, BioSource, NucleicAcid,
                        CvAliasType, SmallMolecule, CvProteinForm, CvInteractionType,
                        Experiment, Complex, CvReferenceQualifier, CvXrefQualifier,
                        CvEvidenceType, CvIdentification, Interaction, CvDevelopmentalStage
                        <br/><br/>
                        <b>Note:</b> Any IntAct type name
                        beginning with Cv is referred to as Cv type from here onwards.
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Overview -->


                <section title="Access" name="editor.access">

                    <blockquote>
                        The URL to access the editor is dependent upon the server where the
                        editor is installed. The general format to access the editor takes the
                        form of:<br/>
                        http://server/intact/editor, where the server part may contain the port
                        depending upon the configuration of the web server.<br/>
                        <br/>
                        To use the editor, you must have a valid account to access the Intact
                        database. The user is presented with a login screen as shown below:<br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-login.jpg" title=""
                             alt="Login Screen" width="1055" height="292"/><br/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        Failure to login with a valid account results in the following error
                        display:<br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-login-error.jpg" title=""
                             alt="Login error" width="1050" height="316"/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Access -->


                <section title="IntAct Types" name="editor.intact.types">

                    <blockquote>
                        This list defines the types available for edit. Before proceeding with
                        any action (search or create), you must select an appropriate type
                        first. <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-types.jpg" title=""
                             alt="IntAct Types" width="772" height="459"/><br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title=""
                             alt="" width="40" height="40" align="left"/>
                        The IntAct type list defaults to the first item (e.g., BioSource) if a type wasn't selected.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- IntAct Types -->


                <section title="Search" name="editor.search">

                    <blockquote>
                        The user must select the type to edit from the drop down list (defaults
                        to the first item in the list if none specified). <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The input field under the drop down list accepts the search criteria.
                        The search is performed first on accession number (ac), and then on
                        short label, primary id and full name respectively. So, it is faster to
                        search by an accession number than by a short label.<br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-sidebar.jpg" title=""
                             alt="IntAct Types" width="1055" height="350"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        You can accept the default search value (*) by simply clicking on the
                        search button. This may take some time depending on the database size as
                        it retrieves all records for given IntAct type. However, you can also
                        use more restrictive filtering such as EBI-3* to restrieve a subset of
                        records. The following screen provides an example to this.<br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-results.jpg" title=""
                             alt="Results page" width="1055" height="370"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        An appropriate message is displayed if a search fails to find any
                        matching records. Click on the AC link to edit individual entry.
                        Alternatively, you can enter the short label directly in the search box
                        and it will take you to the edit screen if a matching record wasn't
                        found for given short label and type as shown below.<br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-search-error.jpg" title=""
                             alt="No Mtach" width="1044" height="200"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title=""
                             alt="" width="40" height="40" align="left"/>
                        The search is carried out against the value in the drop down list. So, ensure that you
                        correctly select the type first before the search.
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- Search -->


                <section title="Cv Editors" name="editor.cv.editors">

                    <blockquote>
                        The create button creates a record for the selected IntAct type. As
                        with the search, it is important to select the appropriate type before
                        clicking on the create button. The following screen shows the result of
                        creating a new CvDatabase record. <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/editor-new-cv.jpg" title=""
                             alt="New CvDatabase" width="1054" height="506"/><br/>
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>

                    <section title="Short Labels" name="editor.short.labels">

                        <blockquote>
                            The current edit type is appended to the main heading (CvDatabase) as
                            shown above. All the drop down list items (topic, database and
                            reference qualifier) are shown as short labels. Except for the
                            short label, all other fields are optional. The user must select 'Save'
                            button to validate the short label. All short labels should be one to
                            twenty characters from the character set blank, 0..9, a-z, : (colon) and
                            -(dash). A dialog box similar to the following will appear for a
                            failure to adhere to this syntax.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-label-client-error.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Incorrect short label" width="416" height="130"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Submitting the form without entering a syntaxically invalid short label
                            results in a server side validation. The error response from the server
                            is shown under the short label as shown below.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-label-server-error.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Short label server validation" width="1038" height="136"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Although both validations are similar in nature, they serve two
                            different purposes. The first validation is performed on the client side
                            (browser) and hence faster of the two. However, the browser must be
                            enabled to accept Javascript for it to work (no dialog window if
                            Javascript is not enabled). This is the preferred validation as it saves
                            extra step in communication with the server. Alternatively, the other
                            validation is not dependent on Javascript and hence guranteed to work on
                            any browser. However, it is slow since it involves a round trip to the
                            server.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            For a short label to be valid it must be syntaxically correct and
                            unique (i.e, no simlar label for the current edit type exists in the
                            database). All the existing short lables for the current edit types are
                            shown along with an error message for a non unique short label entry. <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-label-dup-error.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Duplicate label" width="1041" height="182"/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Short Labels -->


                    <section title="Annotations" name="editor.annotations">

                        <blockquote>
                            Annotations are added by clicking on the Add button in the Annotation
                            section. Associated with each Annotation is a topic which is one of
                            CvTopics available in the database. An error message is displayed when
                            trying to add an annotation without selecting an appropriate type from
                            the drop down lists.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-annot-error.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Annotation error" width="1046" height="108"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            The editing an annotation is similar to adding a new Annotation except
                            for topic and description are already set to their existing values. The
                            screen snapshot given below shows two annotations with one in the
                            editing mode.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-annot-edit.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Editing an Annotation" width="884" height="152"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Annotations -->


                    <section title="Crossreferences" name="editor.xrefs">

                        <blockquote>
                            Similar to Annotations, Crossreferences are added by clicking on the
                            Add button in the Crossreference section. The database drop list
                            consists of short labels for CvDatbase itsm from the IntAct database and
                            the reference qualifier consists of short labels for CvXrefQualifier.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-new-xref.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="New Xref" width="854" height="80"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            As with annotations, the values from drop down lists must be selected
                            prior to adding a crossreference. Editing an existing Crossreference
                            similar to adding a new one except for existing values are shown instead
                            of empty values.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            Any changes to the form are not saved until the form is submitted. So
                            for a new IntAct type, a record is created on the database until the
                            Submit button is clicked and the server reports no errors.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            Editing an existing record is similar to the above except the form is
                            populated with existing data. As shown below, the short label and full
                            name already have their existing values.<br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-edit-cv.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Editing an existing CV object" width="1054" height="594"/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Crossreferences -->

                </section> <!-- Cv Editors -->


                <section title="Other Editors" name="editor.other.editors">

                    <blockquote>
                        Since Cv editor layout is common to all other editors, only the
                        differences are shown for other editors.
                    </blockquote>

                    <section title="BioSource" name="editor.biosource">

                        <blockquote>
                            The biosource editor uses the Newt server to auto-complete the short
                            label and the full name.<br/><br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-new-bs.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Biosource editor" width="636" height="70"/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- BioSource -->


                    <section title="Experiment" name="editor.experiment">

                        <blockquote>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-new-exp.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="New Experiment" width="895" height="75"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            All the above three fields must contain values for a valid Experiment.
                            Need to add more here...
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Experiment -->


                    <section title="Interaction" name="editor.interaction">

                        <blockquote>
                            <img src="./images/editor/editor-int.jpg" title=""
                                 alt="Interaction Editor" width="1026" height="586"/>
                        </blockquote>

                        <section title="Experiments" name="editor.int.experiments">

                            <blockquote>
                                This section describes Experiments already part of the current
                                Interaction. The area below holds experiments not yet added to the
                                Interaction as shown below.<br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/editor-int-exp.jpg" title=""
                                     alt="Experiments not yet added" width="1026" height="196"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                Select Add button to add an experiment or Hide to remove from the
                                collection. Duplcate experiments not allowed.
                            </blockquote>

                        </section> <!-- Experiments -->

                        <section title="Proteins" name="editor.int.proteins">

                            <blockquote>
                                This section lists all the Proteins participated in the cirrent
                                Interaction. For a new Interaction, this section is empty. To add a
                                Protein, you must search for existing Proteins first by provide
                                appropriate values for search fields. Only the most specific value
                                is taken into consideration if multiple values are provided for search.
                                Since IntAct AC is the most specific, other search values are ignored
                                if a value was specified for IntAct AC.<br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/editor-int-prot.jpg" title=""
                                     alt="Adding Proteins" width="1026" height="298"/><br/>
                                <br/>
                                The orange colour bar on the left Protein identfies as new Proteins not
                                yet added to the Interaction. The first Protein is already part of the
                                Interaction and hence for absence of color bar next to it. These
                                'color coded' Proteins do not form part of the current Interaction until
                                the user save them by selecting 'Save' button.<br/>
                                <br/>
                                Any errors in adding Proteins are shown red colour as shown below. <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/editor-int-prot-error.jpg" title=""
                                     alt="Error in adding Proteins" width="1028" height="294"/><br/>
                                <br/>
                                It is an error to add two identical Proteins with similar role. As
                                illustrated in the above example, Protein ABD1 already exists as a bait
                                of the Interaction and adding ABD1 again as a bait caused the
                                above error. The only alternative in this instance is to assign a
                                different role (other than bait) for the new Protein.
                            </blockquote>

                        </section> <!-- Proteins -->

                    </section> <!-- Interaction -->

                </section> <!-- Other Editors -->

                <section title="FAQ" name="editor.faq">

                    <blockquote>
                        <b>What browsers Editor supports?<br/>
                        </b>It has been tested using Mozilla (1.4a), Explorer (6.0) and
                        Konqueror (2.1.1 or above). With the Konqueror it has been noted that
                        pop up windows do not get the focus (need to bring them manually). Also,
                        the footer is almost at the top when a page does not contain much
                        information.<br/><br/>

                        <b>Do I need a JRE installed to run the Editor?</b><br/>
                        No, you don't need Java Runtime to run the Editor as it is designed to
                        run on thin clients (see the next question about JavaScript).<br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>Do I need JavaScript to run the Editor?</b><br/>
                        No but it helps a lot. For example, some validations such as short
                        label syntax are faster as they are peformed via JavaScript. Also, the
                        links to pop up windows wouldn't work when JavaScript is not enabled.
                        However, the overall functionality of the Editor shouldn't be affected
                        if JavaScript is not enabled.<br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>Do I need to logout when I am finished?</b><br/>
                        There is no need to logout because your session will timeout if it has
                        been inactive for 30 or more minutes. However, by explicitly logging out
                        you are releasing the resources (good thing to do). So, we recommend
                        explicit logouts.<br/><br/>

                        <b>Can I connect to my last session when
                            my session expires?</b><br/>
                        No. Once your session expires you need to login again and this in turn
                        will start a new session.<br/><br/>

                        <b>I get an error stack trace for some
                            IntAct types.</b><br/>
                        Not to worry because these types are not implemented yet. This
                        exception shouldn't appear at all once we have implemented all the
                        IntAct types.<br/><br/>

                        <b>Sometimes I get an error when Enter
                            key is pressed for a search string in the sidebar.<br/>
                        </b>This behaviour was observed with Explorer and Konqueror but not
                        with Mozilla. The simple solution is to click on Search button instead.<br/><br/>

                        <b>After entering 'abc' as a short label,
                            I pressed Save and it accepted 'abc' as the short label. Now I entered
                            'ab%' and the form is submitted without any complaints. I thought
                            'ab%' is an invalid short label and the expected error message didn't
                            appear. What is happening?</b><br/>
                        As far as the system is concerned it remembers the value associated
                        with the last 'Save' action. Since you pressed 'Save' after 'abc' but
                        not after 'ab%', it has already assigned 'abc' as the short label. In a
                        nut shell, it is not even aware of 'ab%' because it hasn't seen it.<br/><br/>

                        <b>It hangs for a tax id in BioSource
                            editor.</b><br/>
                        Either Newt server is not accessible or down. There is no way to get
                        around this problem; you need to access the Newt server to do the
                        auto-completion.<br/><br/>

                        <b>Not allowed to save an experiment as
                            it fails with validation errors for drop down lists.</b><br/>
                        Those drop down lists must contain at least a single item for an
                        Experiment to save. Ensure that host organism, interaction detection and
                        participant detection have at least one value in each one of them. If
                        not then use the editor to create values for these (BioSource,
                        CvInteraction and CvIndetification) and return to the Experiment editor.
                        In summary, if you are caught in this situation you need to leave the
                        Experiment editor, create proper entries and then return to it later.<br/><br/>

                        <b>The parameter to search for Proteins
                            given as short label is ignored when a value is provided for IntactAc in
                            the Interaction editor.</b><br/>
                        By default, IntAct AC is the most specific and it is followed by SP AC
                        and finally the short label. Given two values for  short label and
                        IntAct AC, the latter is always given the priority.<br/><br/>

                        <b>Is there a way to save or delete all
                            Proteins in one single click?</b><br/>
                        Not at the moment. We may add this behaviour later.<br/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- FAQ -->

            </section> <!-- Editor -->












            <section title="hierarchView" name="hierarchView">

                <blockquote>
                    HierarchView is a web based application which aims to give the user some basic features
                    in order to visualize the data contained in his IntAct node.
                    <br/><br/>
                    This includes :
                    <ul>
                        <li> Query interface: to select the set of Interactor from which the interaction network is built, </li>
                        <li> Visualising an interaction network as a two dimensional graph, </li>
                        <li> Visualisation of a protein's context (using Search application), </li>
                        <li> Performing action by clicking on a protein of the displayed network, </li>
                        <ul>
                            <li> Center the view, </li>
                            <li> Extend the view, </li>
                        </ul>
                        <li> Displaying GO terms of all proteins from which the interaction network is built, </li>
                        <li> Displaying the GO hierarchy of a selected GO term </li>
                        <li> Highlighting all proteins annotated by a specific GO term (selected by the user) </li>
                    </ul>
                </blockquote>


                <section title="Availability" name="hierarchView.availability">

                    <blockquote>
                        The application to visualize protein interaction network is available if
                        you can fulfill the software dependencies requirement such as
                        <a href="http://www.tulip-software.org/" target="_blank">Tulip</a>
                        which allows to perform the graphical rendering.
                        However, if those dependencies are sorted out, the user just need a read access
                        to the database to use it.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>


                <section title="Graphical user interface" name="hierarchView.GUI">

                    <blockquote>
                        The graphical user interface is integrates:
                        <p>
                            <u>a sidebar</u>
                            <blockquote>
                                <p>
                                    <u>the basic sidebar</u>:
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    Some components of the sidebar are always visible whatever the state of the application.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    This includes:
                                    <ul>
                                        <li> on the top, the query interface. </li>
                                        <li> on the bottom, a set of IntAct related link. </li>
                                    </ul>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>the advanced sidebar</u>:
                                    After loading a first interaction network, more features are available in the sidebar :
                                    <ul>
                                        <li> below the query interface, the <i>Graph</i> menu which allows to expand and
                                            contract the current interaction network,</li>
                                        <li> above the link section, the mouse-click behaviour section which allows the user to
                                            switch the mouse-click behaviour either to center the view or add a new network.</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </p>
                            </blockquote>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <u>a content frame</u>
                            <blockquote>
                                <p>
                                    <u>PPIN header</u>: it specifies from which protein(s) is built the current interaction network
                                    as well as the number of nodes and edges. If needed, the selected GO term used for the
                                    highlightis displayed.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>PPIN content</u>: a clickable image representing the requested interaction network.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>highlight top</u>: a list of GO terms related to the set of proteins from which the
                                    current interaction network has been generated.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>highlight bottom</u>: After selecting one of the GO term displayed in the top right frame,
                                    the related GO hierarchy is displayed, allowing the user to perform a highlight by
                                    selecting on the GO term of the hierarchy.
                                </p>
                            </blockquote>
                        </p>

                        <center>
                            <table border="0">
                                <tr>
                                    <td> <a href="./images/hierarchView/PPIN.png" target="_blank"><img src="./images/hierarchView/PPIN-small.png" border="0"></img></a> </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td> click the image to enlarge </td>
                                </tr>
                            </table>
                        </center>
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- GUI -->


                <section title="What is an interaction network ?" name="hierarchView.PPIN">

                    <blockquote>
                        It is a graphical way of representing an protein protein interaction network as
                        a two dimensional graph structure. Within that graph, the nodes represent proteins
                        and the edges a physical interaction.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The entry point of an interaction network is an <b>Interactor</b> (either <b>Protein</b>
                        or <b>Interaction</b>) around which we will look for all Interactors within a specified
                        threshold called depth. A depth 1 would be all direct Interactor of the selected protein.
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- What is an interaction network ? -->


                <section title="How to display an interaction network ?" name="hierarchView.display">

                    <blockquote>
                        Type in the <i>Interactor</i> form either a protein short label or accession number and
                        click the <i>search</i> button to display the related interaction network. You are free
                        to type a comma separated list of proteins in order to display all of them in one go.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The visualization systems shows all specified proteins with a bold font. As soon as the
                        interaction network is displayed, the user interface is changing slightly to offer more
                        interactivity.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        When querying IntAct to display an interaction network, if the query is ambiguous (e.g.
                        the query <i>snu*</i> could describes several proteins such as snu66, snu13...),
                        you will be automatically forwarded to the search application where you will be able to
                        select the targeted protein(s).
                    </blockquote>

                </section> <!-- How to display an interaction network ? -->


                <section title="How to interact with the interaction network ?" name="hierarchView.PPIN.interact">

                    <section title="Add a further interaction network" name="hierarchView.PPIN.add">

                        <blockquote>
                            When adding a interaction network, a new one is generated according to the user's wishes
                            and then fusionned to the current one to display them alltogether.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            There is two ways of doing it:
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    Type in the <i>Interactor</i> form either a protein short label or AC and click
                                    the <i>add</i> button. You are free to type a comma separated list of
                                    protein in order to display all of them in one go.
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    If the protein of interrest is available in the current interaction network, you
                                    can switch the mouse-click (sidebar) behaviour to <i>add a network</i> then click
                                    on the wanted protein.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Add a further interaction network -->


                    <section title="Center the view" name="hierarchView.PPIN.center">

                        <blockquote>
                            In order to navigate in the interaction network, you can decide to change the current
                            central protein. To do so, switch the mouse-click (sidebar) behaviour to
                            <i>center the view</i>, then, click on the wanted protein. The current interaction
                            network will be reloaded as the interaction network of the selected protein.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Bear in mind that it would have had the same effect to type the short label or accession
                            number of the protein in the <i>Interactor</i> form and clicked on the <i>search</i>
                            button.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Center the view -->


                    <section title="Expand the current interaction network" name="hierarchView.PPIN.expand">

                        <blockquote>
                            In order to improve the readability and the loading time, the default depth of an
                            interaction network has been set relatively low. Nevertheless you can increase that
                            parameter in order to expand the current interaction network by clicking the <i>expand</i>
                            button in the sidebar. Bear in mind that there is a minimum and maximum depth, this
                            implies the <i>expand</i> (<i>contract</i>) button to disapear when the maximum (minimum)
                            depth is reached.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Expand the current interaction network -->


                    <section title="Highlight the interaction network" name="hierarchView.PPIN.highlight">
                        <blockquote>
                            After loading an interaction network, a list of GO terms specific to the set of selected
                            proteins is displayed in the top right frame of hierarchView. By clicking on one of them,
                            the related GO hierarchy appears in the bottom right frame (powered by
                            <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ego" target="_blank">QuickGo</a>).
                            If a single GO term is found, the hierarchy is displayed automaticaly.
                            Now You can select one of the displayed GO term of the hierarchy in order to highlight
                            in the interaction network all proteins annotated with that GO term in IntAct.
                            These proteins will appear with a different color label.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            In the displayed hierarchy, the lower GO term is the more specific, and the higher you go,
                            the most generic the GO terms become. Bear in mind that when selecting a GO term in the
                            displayed hierarchy the highlight is done with a set of GO terms including the selected one
                            and all its children (i.e. until the most specific).
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <center>
                                <table border="0">
                                    <tr>
                                        <td><a href="./images/hierarchView/highlight.png" target="_blank"><img src="./images/hierarchView/highlight-small.png" border="0"></img></a> </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td> click the image to enlarge </td>
                                    </tr>
                                </table>
                            </center>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section> <!-- Highlight the interaction network -->

                </section> <!-- How to interact -->

            </section> <!-- hierarchView -->

        </section> <!-- applications -->

    </division>

</page>
